Guide to the Obadiah Bruen Brown Family papers, 1807-1941 MS2253
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Obadiah Bruen Brown Family papers
1807-1941
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Train, Russell E.
MS2253
0.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains documents related to the family of Obadiah Bruen Brown and the records date from 1807-1941. Brown was the pastor of the First Baptist Church in Washington for more than 40 years. He also served as the first President of the Board of Trustees of Columbian College (now George Washington University). The materials in the collection includes letters, wills, deeds and GW course lecture cards.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Russell Train, 2008 (Accession 2008.028).
Historical or Biographical Note
Obadiah Bruen Brown (1779-1853) arrived in the city of Washington in 1807 as the first pastor of the First Baptist Church. Born in Newark New Jersey, Brown left home at the age of 17 to study with Baptist Reverend William Van Horne in Scotch Plains, New Jersey. In 1807 at the age of 28, he preached several sermons at the First Baptist Church andy soon after was called to become the pastor. The same year Obadiah Brown become pastor he also began working at the Post Office Department and was elected chaplain of the House of Representatives. He started as a clerk in the Post Office and eventually held the position of Chief of the Contract Division. He married Elizabeth Riley Jackson in 1808. They had four children.
In 1820, Obadiah Brown was an active delegate to the Baptist General Convention in Philadelphia. The delegates to the convention decided to open a Baptist institution of higher education in the District of Columbia. On February 9, 1821, President James Monroe signed the legislation that passed Congress granting a charter for the Columbian College (now George Washington University) which opened later that year. Brown served as the first President of the Board of Trustees of the college and was an instrumental contributor to the first building fund.
Obadiah Brown died May 2, 1853 at age 73. He is buried in Oak Hill Cemetery as are his wife Elizabeth, son William and several grandchildren.
Other members of the Brown family included in this collection include William Van Horne Brown and Thomas B. Brown, Obadiah Brown's sons and George Whitfield Brown one of his grandson.
Most of the information about the Obadiah Brown in this biography comes from Russell Train's book The Train Family. This book relates much of the history of the Brown family. It is cataloged in the Special Collections and serves as a great resource for anyone researching the Obadiah Brown and the Brown family.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains letters, deeds, wills, one photograph, one postcard, and GWU course lecture cards all related to the family of Russell Train. The three prominent members of the family represented in the collection are Obadiah Bruen Brown, his son William Van Horne Brown, and Obadiah's grandson George Whitfield Brown. The material dates from 1807-1941.
The material is for the most part organized in the order established by the Donor Russell Train and retains the original folder headings. This does mean that some folders duplicate types of documents and perhaps overlap in dates. As the collection is small enough Special Collection staff deemed that retraining this order did not unduly inhibit a researcher from discovering all important information.
Collection Organization
This collection is not organized into series.
Baptists; Columbian College; Washington (D.C.); First Baptist Church (Washington, D.C.); George Washington University; Brown, O. B. (Obadiah Bruen)
- Brown family genealogy includes notes on O.B.B. [Obadiah Bruen Brown], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters and other papers related to the Brown family, 1807-1831 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  General note
  This file includes Obadiah Bruen Brown's Will.
- Letter from William Van Horne Brown of Washington, DC to Bro. Yost (Potts town?), 01/05/1861 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Brown, George Whitfield and Mary [1/2], 1870 ca.-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Brown, George Whitfield and Mary [2/2], 1870 ca.-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Obadiah Bruen Brown, 1853-1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Brown, Obadiah and Elizabeth Riley, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Brown, (O.B) [Obadiah Bruen] and Brown (W.V.) [William Van Horne], 1832-1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Obadiah Brown a thesis by John C. Hillhouse Jr., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  This file also contains two articles about Obadiah Brown written by John C. Hillhouse. These items were sent by Mr. Hillhouse to Russell Train.
- Death of Obadiah B. Brown, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  This folder contains a newspaper article
- Oration by Thomas B. Brown, 07/04/1830 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Oration Delivered before the citizens of Lafayette Indiana Commemorating the anniversary of our Independence July 4, 1830 by Thomas B. Brown"
- Bruen family, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Geneaology related to the Bruen family
- Correspondence, 1854-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Historic documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Misc. deeds etc. involving Obadiah Bruen Brown, 1822-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Old papers, some family some interest, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Course cards for GW courses, 1832-1834 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  According to Donor Russell Train these cards belonged to William Van Horne Brown, son of Obadiah Brown. He received an A.B degree in 1831, an M.D. degree in 1834, and an M.A. degree in 1838 all from George Washington University (known at the time as Columbian College).